<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good news from Scotland: being a true relation of the present condition of the Army under the command of Lieut. Gen. Crumwel; and of the Marquesse of Arguile's taking a ship coming from Denmark laden with ten thousand arms: with the articles about the surrender of Barwick; and the disbanding of the forces under the Lord Lanerick and Monro: as it was sent in a letter from Lieut. General Crumwels quarters neer Berwick, to a friend in London.</title>
            <author>J. L.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L29</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E465_34</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205210</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864641</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864641</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116873</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88488)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116873)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 74:E465[34])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good news from Scotland: being a true relation of the present condition of the Army under the command of Lieut. Gen. Crumwel; and of the Marquesse of Arguile's taking a ship coming from Denmark laden with ten thousand arms: with the articles about the surrender of Barwick; and the disbanding of the forces under the Lord Lanerick and Monro: as it was sent in a letter from Lieut. General Crumwels quarters neer Berwick, to a friend in London.</title>
                  <author>J. L.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert at the black Spread-Eagle at the West end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: J: L.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] ye 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116873:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <p>GOOD News from Scotland: Being A TRUE RELATION Of the preſent condition of the ARMY under the Command of Lieut. Gen. CRUMWEL;</p>
            <p>And of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Arguile</hi>'s taking a Ship coming from <hi>Denmark</hi> laden with ten thouſand Arms: With the ARTICLES about the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render of <hi>BARWICK;</hi> and the Diſbanding of the Forces under the Lord <hi>Lanerick</hi> and <hi>Monro:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it was ſent in a LETTER from Lieut. General <hi>Crumwels</hi> Quarters neer <hi>Berwick,</hi> to a Friend in LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <date>
                  <add>8ber y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </add>
               </date>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the black Spread-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116873:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <head>
               <hi>News from</hi> Scotland: As it was ſent in a LETTER from Lieut: General <hi>Cromwels</hi> Quarters, to a Friend in <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have much wondred, that having ſo frequently writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten unto you, I could never receive as much as one Letter from you: Whatever the reaſon was, Charity wiſhes me to imagine it to be either your not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my Letters, or elſe your not knowing how yours might be conveyed unto me. I invite you once more by this, to hold a conſtant Correſpondence; which if you do, I ſhall give you a weekly Account of our proceedings in theſe Northern parts. We have now drawn the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of our Army into <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Van quarters this night within ten miles of <hi>Edenburgh:</hi> there is part of the Army left behinde to block up <hi>Berwick;</hi> two Regiments of Foot, and the Lieut. Generals Regiment of Horſe block it up on the Engliſh ſide, we have others that keep ſtrong Guards on <hi>Scotland</hi> ſide. The Lieut. General, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116873:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
and Officers, expreſs very great tenderneſs to that Kingdom, in being very careful that the Soldiers give no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence juſtly to the Inhabitants, by Plundring, or being other-ways uncivil. Upon our firſt entrance into <hi>Scotland,</hi> a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment lately raiſed in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham</hi> behaved themſelves rudely; which as ſoon as the Lieut: General had notice of, he cauſed it to Rend<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zvouz upon Tweed Banks, and the Scottiſh people having challenged ſeveral Horſes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them by that Regiment, which the Lieut: General cauſed to be reſtored back, and the Plunderers to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiered; a Lieutenant that countenanced ſuch deeds, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vered into the Marſhal hands, and the Colonel himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niving at them, and not doing Juſtice upon the Offendors when C<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mplaints were brought to him, was taken from the head of his Regiment, and ſuſpended from executing his Place, until he had anſwered at a Councel of War for his neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in the performance of his Duty. This notable and impartial piece of Juſtice did very much take with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the Regiment is ordered back into <hi>Northumberland.</hi> Friday laſt 22 of Septem. the Marquis of <hi>Argyle,</hi> the Lord <hi>Elcoe,</hi> Sir <hi>John Scot,</hi> and others, came as Commiſſioners from the honeſt Party in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to the Lord of <hi>Mording<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> houſe at <hi>Mordington,</hi> to the Lieut: Generals quarters two miles from <hi>Berwick</hi> within <hi>Scotland;</hi> we went all to meet him four miles from the houſe: That night my Lord ſent in a Trumpet to <hi>Berwick,</hi> for a ſafe Conduct for the ſaid Lord <hi>Elcoe,</hi> and the reſt of the Commiſſioners; which being granted by the Governor, they were Conducted in the next morning: Little or nothing could be done by them to the gaining of the Town. The Lords day my Lord ſent in to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Governor himſelf to come forth, which he accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly did: After much Debate he was brought to this, To deſire to ſend two Gentlemen to <hi>Lanerick</hi> and <hi>Monro,</hi> to know their pleaſure concerning the ſurrender of that Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Monday morning the Gentlemen went, having the Lieutenant Generals Paſs, and a Letter from the Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116873:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
We fall to our-buſineſs in order to our taking the Town; and the Lords day at night Colonel <hi>Pride</hi> poſſeſſed himſelf of Tweed mouth, and the Bridge foot on the Engliſh ſide, and the next night he blew up the houſe of Guard which they had built upon the Bridge: We are very near them by the Scottiſh ſide, having driven away many of their Sheep from under the wall. Monday in the forenoon there came an Expreſs from General <hi>Leven</hi> and Lieut. Gen. <hi>David Leſley,</hi> certifying my Lord Marquis, that they were very like to agree upon the old Treaty, which was to hold no longer then that night: The Conditions, in caſe they do agree, will be theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That both the Armies, that under the Lord Marqueſs <hi>Arguile,</hi> and that under <hi>Lanerick,</hi> with all Forces in any of the Garriſons in the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> together with <hi>Berwick</hi> and <hi>Carliſle</hi> be disbanded.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the ſecuring and ſetling Religion at home, and promoting the work of Reformation abroad, both in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> be referred to the determination of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly or their Commiſſioners, and that all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and civill differences whatſoever be referred to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of a Parliament ſpeedily to be called.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That to prevent the ruine of Religion and breacd with <hi>England,</hi> no party that were in the late engagement againſt <hi>England,</hi> may be of the new Parliament or generall Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Cockermouth</hi> briefly thus; It hath been a long time beſieged by 500 Countrymen. The Lieutenant Generall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> forces under Colonel <hi>Aſhton,</hi> with Colonel <hi>Brigs</hi> his horſe, together with Colonel <hi>Hacker</hi> and Colonel <hi>Whites</hi> Regiments of Horſe, from <hi>Pontefract</hi> to march up to their reliefe; they might have been there three weeks agoe, but are not yet come up. The honeſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116873:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
Governour Lieutenant <hi>Bird</hi> hot<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s out gallantly; he hath a fortnights proviſion yet. The Enemy had mined very near the wall, he ſallyed out, killed and took them all that were at work, and brought away their Tools, and burnt the barn that ſheltered them. He can hold out one part of the Caſtle, though they ſhould take the other, but I hope he will be releived ſuddenly, for that I heare there are Forces upon their march towards them. The Marqueſſe of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile</hi> took ſeven daies ago a ſhip with ten thouſand Arms that came from <hi>Denmark,</hi> intended for Duke <hi>Hamilton;</hi> they came to <hi>Leith,</hi> where they were ſeized upon. There are about eighty Officers armed that ran away from Duke <hi>Hamiltons</hi> Army; now lurking about <hi>Cheviot</hi> Hills, wee have ſent one hundred and twenty Horſe of the Lieutenant Generalls Regiment, and forty Dragoons towards them, which we hope will be able to give a good account of that buſineſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi>
               <lb/>
The Godly Party in <hi>Scotland</hi> ſeem to be very ſenſible of the benefit they have lately reaped by the victory God gave to our Army, and ſay they hope never to forget thoſe Inſtruments which the Lord choſe to work their delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and check themſelves for the hard thoughts they formerly had of this Army: And its very obſerveable, That this Army which the honeſt Party in <hi>Scotland</hi> looked upon as a Bundle of Sectaries, not fit to be continued, and did many ways unjuſtly reproach, ſhould now, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, be the onely authors of their Deliverance. Some of the moſt eminent and honorable in <hi>Scotland</hi> have inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly confeſſed to me their error and raſhneſs in charging the Army laſt year with Rebellion unjuſtly, ſeeing now there is a neceſſity put upon them to tread in that very path: Nay, they acted now againſt a clearer Authority, where was the concurrence of the three States, King, Lords and Commons, I am much perſwaded that the Lord hath
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116873:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
a glorious work in <hi>Scotland</hi> as well as in <hi>England.</hi> The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the godly people in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as to the Civil, was once different from that of the godly people in <hi>England,</hi> or at leaſt acted as it had been different; but now the Lord hath been pleaſed ſo to order the Affairs of that Kingdom, as that the Intereſt of the godly people there, is become the ſame with ours in <hi>England,</hi> and they and we muſt act upon the ſame Grounds and Principles: And I am perſwaded, that ſo much of their Power as the Princes of the Earth have lent to the ſupport of that Man of Sin, God hath and will ſuddenly utterly break and deſtroy. I have no more at preſent, but that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Mordington</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> 
                  <date>Sept. 27. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt affectionate Friend, J: L.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
